Good morning everyone, my name is Longjie. In this presenttion I'd like to talk about what is inside the nuclei.
Well, let's begin with one question. Have you ever wondered what is the universe made of ?
Or what are humnan beings made of?
Let's consider a simpler question
What is water made of?
From high school learning we've understood that
water is made of water molecular
But what is moceluar made of?
Well, they're made of atoms.
And for water, it is made of H atoms and O atom.
And what is H atom made of ?
Well in college we've understood that H atom is made of electron and proton.
Next question is waht is proton made of?
Well let's begin some history
Discovery of the proton can be tracked back to 1917 when E. Rutherford performed
the scattering of nitrogen atom and α particle.
Another crucial discovery was made
15 years later by J. Chadwick in his prominent paper with an announcement on possible existence of the new particle named neutron.
Those nucleons were first accepted as elementary particles in nature.
However, a large number of new nucleon-like particles(hadrons in the present day)were discovered with the development of experimental technologies, which revealed that the nucleons are not the most fundamental building blocks
Nowadays, we understood that protons are composed of quarks and gluons (u quark u quark and d quark)
Now we can answer what is the universe made of and human beings made of.
And we are made of atoms. Every atom in your body hides a whirlwind of
quarks and gluons, raging at nearly the speed of light!
One may ask how we study them, or how we see the unseeable ?
Well, we study them via colliding of particles.
Here I listed Electron-Ion Collider.
One can see that particles will be accelerated in some rings, and collide at certain locations.
We will measure productions of collisions, and compare the experimental data with the theoretical predictions.
To figure out if there exists new particles or physics beyond standard model.
Specifically, one scattering can be demonstarted as follows.
Here l denotes leptons, bottom line denotes protons.
Here electron penetrates deep into the proton, will produce new particles.
We measure X, or the new particles.
One may ask, why It matters?
Well, there are many unsolved mysteries in particle physics.
The first is spin puzzle, where the measured quark spin contribution was found to be small
(4% ∼ 24%) to the proton spin.
Which means that we need to take consideration of angular momentum, or the contribution from orbital angular momentum of gluons.
The next is asymmetry of mater and antimatter.
Universe is dominated by matter, not antimatter. We want to find the origin, and test it on collider.
Why collider? Because it will provide the most exreme environment(100000 hotter than heart of sun).
Add next is about the dark matter, or physics beyond the standard model.
In standard model, dark matter and its origin of mass is not included.
So we want to construct the theory that could describe it, and test on colliders.
Thanks for llistening!